This is PowerShell Breakdown One-Liners
where the entire script is written in just one line.
(Ba-da-dum-tish)
OK, now here's the real one.
This one finds all of the Active Directory accounts
that are locked out within an Organizational Unit
and then unlocks them all.
This really comes in handy
when something causes large numbers of users
to have their accounts become locked.
When the IT team becomes overwhelmed
with support calls,
you can run this one-liner
to stave off the angry mob long enough
so you can fix whatever that something is.
The command that unlocks accounts
is called Unlock-ADAccount
and it is fairly simple to use and understand.
We only need to be concerned
with the -Identity parameter,
which identifies the account to unlock.
I typically use the SAM account name
to identify a user.
It can be found in ADUC
by double-clicking on the user,
selecting the "Account" tab,
and looking under "User Logon Name (Pre-Windows 2000)".
I'll go ahead and copy the SAM account name to the clipboard.
You can also use any of these,
which are found in the "Attribute Editor" tab
We know that Michelle's account
is locked out by this message here.
Now we can paste the SAM account name
into PowerShell by right-clicking.
Hit ENTER
and verify the account is unlocked in ADUC.
The message that was there before is now gone,
so the account is now unlocked.
That's how you unlock an account.
Now I'll show you how to search
for all of the accounts that are currently locked out.
The command we're using this time
is Search-ADAccount.
This searches Active Directory
for various things like
expired or inactive accounts,
expired passwords,
and what we're using it for:
locked out accounts.
We'll use two parameters with this command:
The first is -LockedOut.
This will return the accounts
that are currently locked out.
The second is -SearchBase.
This tells PowerShell where to search.
Without it, PowerShell will search the entire domain.
Since we want to search only
in a specific Organizational Unit,
we need to input the OU here
in Distinguished Name format.
To find the Distinguished Name
of an Organizational Unit in ADUC,
right-click on the OU,
select "Properties",
and it will be listed in the "Attribute Editor" tab.
You can simply copy the Distinguished Name
from the Attribute Editor
and right-click to paste into PowerShell.
Add quotes around the Distinguished Name
and we're good to go.
We can combine Search-ADAccount
and Unlock-ADAccount
together with the pipe ( | )
to unlock all accounts
that are currently locked out.
Since the command on the left
outputs the identities of accounts,
we don't need to use the -Identity parameter
for the command on the right of the pipe.
Verify that the account are unlocked
by spot-checking in ADUC
or re-run the Search-ADAccount command.
No results are returned,
so that tells us that no accounts
are currently locked out.
That's it!
That's all there is to it.
As always, the script shown in the video,
the write-up, and the supporting scripts
will be uploaded to my GitHub
which is linked in the description.
Thank you for watching.
I hope you learned something.