Hello, in this video series I will be breaking down my PowerShell script
that finds all of the Active Directory groups that one user is a member of
and makes another user a member of those same groups.
This procedure is also commonly known as "permissions mirroring"
and is used to grant one user the same access rights and permissions of another user.
To demonstrate the manual procedure that our script will automate
We'll first open Active Directory Users and Computers
Double-click on the user to use as a reference
Select the **MemberOf** tab
Keep window open somewhere on the screen where it is visible
Double-click on the user to add to groups
Select the **MemberOf** tab, click **Add...**
Enter the names of the groups from the reference user, seperated by a semicolon (`;`)
Verify the group names with **Check Names**
Click **OK** and **OK** again
While the manual process isn't too cumbersome in our example,
we can use PowerShell to automate this.
In Part 1, I'll show the core script and cover the `Get-ADUser` and `Add-ADGroupMember` commands,
as well as how to store objects as a variable,
and how you can use output of one command as input of another using the pipeline.
In Part 2, we'll add the `Out-GridView` command to the script
to give you an interactive window so you can
select specific groups to add the user to.
Finally, in Part 3, we'll put everything together into an advanced function
and add it to a PowerShell module for long-term reuse.