Hey guys and gals
welcome to Part 3 of the breakdown of my script
which finds all the Active Directory groups
that one user is a member of
and makes another user a member of those same groups.
In this final part,
we'll take our script that we've written in Parts 1 & 2
and add it to an advanced function
which will turn it into a reusable tool
just like native PowerShell cmdlets.
It has positional parameters.
A positional parameter assumes the name of the parameter
by position that you input values.
It will receive input from pipeline.
With this feature,
you can then integrate it into other scripts
and/or use it in conjunction with other commands.
It has switch parameters.
Switch parameters are kind of a toggle (on/off) "switch"
in which no extra input is needed
such as the -UsePicker parameter
which allows us the option
of using the Out-GridView window to select the groups
and the -PassThru parameter
gives us the option of outputting the groups
that our target user was added
to the console.
This could be useful if you wanted to log/document the action
or pass those groups through the pipeline to another command.
The heart of an advanced function
is found inside the process block.
You can also think of it as the engine
and it's where most of the logic will be placed.
If we compare the process block
with our script from Part 2,
we can see many similarities.
Variable names have slightly changed,
and two "if" statements are added
to take action if the switch parameter is used.
Otherwise, they're the same
because they perform the same core function.
Since the core part of the script is the same,
we're really just changing how it's used.
To create an advanced function,
start by typing "function"
and click on "advanced function".
We see that it's given us
a good template to work with.
Now's a good time
to give the function a name
ensuring that it follows the verb dash noun format
for consistancy with other PowerShell functions and commands.
We can see that the CmdletBinding
is already there for us.
This is what makes a function
an advanced function
and unlocks these features
that I previously described.
We'll begin by adding our first parameter.
In the param block,
simply start typing "parameter"
and choose the "parameter declaration snippet".
In the previous video's script,
the first variable that was created
was the $ReferenceUser variable,
so let's use that as our first parameter.
By default
the order in which we place parameters
will determine the parameter position,
so it also makes sense
to start with $ReferenceUser.
We'll give it a brief description like
"User who's group membership to use as a reference".
Just something so you get an idea
of what the parameter is used for.
Next, we want to give the parameter some attributes.
Because the function will not work
without the reference user,
we will make this parameter "Mandatory".
If you were to attempt
to use the command
without the mandatory parameter,
PowerShell will ask you to input something
before proceeding.
Because this is mandatory,
we should also add a Help Message
to let the person using the command
know what kind of information is mandated.
We also need to seperate the attributes
by a comma ( , )
to let PowerShell know
that we're starting a new attribute
and it's not just a continuation
of something before it.
The last attribute we'll add
is ValueFromPipeline
to enable this parameter to receive input
from the pipeline.
Since there are more than one attribute,
we'll place each one on a new line
to make it easier to read.
The parameter type
determines how PowerShell
treats the input object.
For example:
"2" can be either a number
(known as an integer)
or text
(known as a string).
So if we type:
integer of two,
times integer of two,
we get four.
But if we type: string two
times string two,
we'll get twenty-two,
because it combines strings together.
Since we're mimicking some functionality
of the Get-ADUser cmdlet,
as well as to ensure interoperability with it,
I'm going to use the type from the documentation.
In this case, it's "ADUser".
Before we add a new parameter,
we need to add a comma ( , )
after the $ReferenceUser variable
to indicate that there will be a
follow-on parameter.
We'll add a 2nd parameter
similar to the 1st,
and make a couple  adjustments
for the -TargetUser parameter.
Since this is not going to receive input from the pipeline,
we'll leave that out.
Just like with the Add-ADGroupMember command
from our previous video,
we want to be able to add
one or more users to a group,
so we'll add an opening and closing bracket ( [] )
after "ADPrincipal".
As I've mentioned earlier,
a switch parameter is like a toggle (on/off) switch
in which no extra input is needed.
These will not be mandatory
and will have no attributes.
To simplify the Begin, Process, and End blocks
(also known as Advanced Methods)
he Begin block is for one-time preprocessing
the Process block is for multiple record processing,
and this block is required at a minimum
for processing input from the pipeline
the End block for one-time post-processing.
Because we're not doing any pre or post processing,
and the -ReferenceUser parameter
is receiving input from the pipeline,
only the process block will be used.
Since we've already written most of the script logic,
let's use the previous script as a guide
for what to place in the process block.
We'll add the "if" statements
where we would want to use the switch parameters.
Now that we've finished the logic portion,
let's add some comment-based help.
Comment-based help is a way
to add helpful information
to your advanced function
that can be retrieved with the Get-Help command.
It's called "comment-based"
because you use it in a block comment.
The position of the comment-based help
should be placed after the "function"
and before the Param block.
Comment-based help is triggered
when you use certain keywords.
While all keywords will probably go unused,
I would recommend that at a minimum,
that a description or synopsys
and examples of the function
be added to the comment block.
Now that we've finished writing the funciton,
save it with a .psm1 file extension
in the PowerShell modules folder.
Import the newly created module,
and then we can use the Copy-ADGroupMembership command in PowerShell.
(Music: "Energy" from Bensound.com)
This is the end of the three-part video series
where I took you on a PowerShell coding journey
starting with a basic script,
adding some cool features to it,
and concluded with an advanced function.
All of the scripts shown in the videos,
as well as the writeup will be on my GitHub,
linked in the description.
If you found the video useful,
push that "like" button
I'll be uploading more videos regularly
so make sure that you're subscribed.
Thank you for watching,
and I hope you learned something.