Hello and welcome to Part 1 of the video series
where we write a PowerShell script that automates the process
of adding a new Active Directory user
to all of the groups of an existing user.
This is what our script will look like at the end of the video.
It's only three lines of code,
but that little bit will save you time and energy in the future.
We'll begin by creating a new file
and saving it with a .ps1 file extension.
I'll keep the finished version on the left side
so we can following along as we write the script.
Whenever I write a script,
way before I even start writing any code,
I like to map out the logical progression that the script will follow.
I'll do this in the form of comments
which start with a '#'.
Everything after the '#'
will not be run by PowerShell
and is used for any notes, reminders,
or explanations that you'd want to put in.
For this script, it's a three-step process:
1. Get the reference user along with group memberships
2. Isolate the group identities from the reference user
3. Add the new user to those groups
First, I'll explain how to use the Get-ADUser command
to get information about the reference user
and the groups that she is a member of.
If we just run the Get-ADUser command by itself,
PowerShell won't know from which user to get the information for
and the command won't work.
We want to identify Michelle as the user to get.
To identify Michelle as the user,
we'll use the -Identity parameter.
Parameters are extra bits of information
that you're adding to the command
to narrow the scope or help specify the task
that you're telling PowerShell to do
and they always start with a dash ( - ).
Get-ADUser has many parameters
and I may show those later in some other videos,
but for now, I'm only going to be concerned with the -Identity parameter.
The command is going to look like:
Get-ADUser -Identity USER
USER can be identified by:
Distinguished Name
Globally Unique Identifier
the Security Identifier
or the SAM Account Name
I, personally, like to use the SAM account name
because it's almost universally accepted
in PowerShell commands,
and it's usually short and easy to remember.
The SAM account name can be found in Active Directory Users and Computers.
Now, I've heard it pronounced A-D-U-C,
Ay-duck, or a duck,
but saying that we're going to look for Michelle
inside a duck just sounds kind of silly,
so I'm just going to pronounce it "A-D-U-C"
The SAM account name can be found
by double-clicking on the user,
selecting the Account tab,
and it'll be under "User Logon Name (Pre-Windows 2000)"".
You can find each of the other identifiers in ADUC
by going to the toolbar at the top,
clicking on View, and ensure Advanced Features are enabled.
Then double-click on the user
and select the Attribute Editor tab.
Now that we've got the correct identity of our example user, Michelle,
we're ready to use the command.
So we'll type in:
Get-ADUser -Identity michelle.adams
By default, the Get-ADUser command
returns these 10 bits of information about the user.
These bits are called "properties",
and every PowerShell object has them.
If you want to retrieve additional properties with Get-ADUser,
you must use the -Properties parameter.
If you want too view all properties of a user,
use the asterisk ( * ) wildcard.
You'll type:
Get-ADuser -Identity michelle.adams -Properties *
That's the MemberOf property,
and it shows all of the groups that Michelle is a member of.
For our script, we want the MemberOf property,
so we'll type it in as:
We can see the same 10 properties as before,
with an additional 11th that shows Michelle's group membership.
These groups are in Distinguished Name format,
which isn't easy to read or type,
but that's OK because in the next segment,
we're going to store these group names in memory
so we don't actually have to ever type them.
PowerShell objects can be stored using something called "variables".
After a variable is assigned a value,
we can then call it later
to return the stored object.
Variables can be things may things,
but the most common are
numbers, text, or PowerShell objects.
They are represented by text strings
that begin with a dollar sign ( $ )
such as $a,
$process
or $my_var
Names of variables, like most everything in PowerShell,
are not case-sensitive.
They can be UPPERCASE,
lowercase,
PascalCase,
which is capitalizing the first letter of each word,
without using spaces,
or anything in between.
To create a new variable,
use an assignment statement to assign a value to it.
I'll start by typing:
$text as our variable name,
then an equal sign ( = ),
then the text inside quotes ( '' ).
The assignment statement can be used
with or without spaces around the equals sign ( = ),
but with spaces are the recommened style
to make it easier to read when scripting.
Keep in mind that without the assignment statement,
the default value of all variables is "null",
that is, nothing or without value.
If you try to call a variable before it's been assigned a value,
you'll get nothing in return.
Let's assign the output of our previously used Get-ADUser command
to the variable name $ReferenceUser.
We'll type:
$ReferenceUser = Get-ADUser -Identity michelle.adams -Properties MemberOf
Once we hit ENTER,
no output will be given during a variable assignment.
We then recall the output of the command stored,
by simply typing in the variable name.
If we type $ReferenceUser,
we'll get the output just the same
as if we were to type in the command by itself.
We now have completed the first segement of the script.
Go ahead and copy that from PowerShell into our script.
If we want to return an individual property
of an object being stored as a variable,
we can type the variable name,
then a dot ( . ),
then the property name.
If we type:
$ReferenceUser.MemberOf
We have can isolate the groups
that we want to add the new user to.
Let's assign the groups to the $SelectedGroups  variable
to complete the second part of our script.
The final step in our script
is to add our new user, Paul,
to the selected groups with the Add-ADGroupMember command.
The Add-ADGroupMember command works like:
Add-ADGroupMember -Identity GROUPNAME -Members NEWUSER
The -Identity parameter for this command
specifies the group that's receiving the new members.
You can identify a group by the same ways as Get-ADUser:
Again, I prefer to use SAM account name.
The -Members parameter specifies the new members to add to a group.
You can identify new members
by the same ways as you can with the -Identity parameter.
SAM account name is always a safe bet.
To demonstrate the Add-ADGroupMember command,
let's add Paul to the Sales group.
We can find the SAM account names of groups
just like we find the SAM account name of users
by going in ADUC,
double-clicking on the group,
then finding the "Pre-Windows 2000" name.
We'll type:
Add-ADGroupMember -Identity Sales -Members paul.allen
No output is given,
but we can confirm that the command worked
by looking in ADUC.
Now, we will want do the last step
and add Paul to the four groups that Michelle is a member of.
If we try:
Add-ADGroupMember -Identity $SelectedGroups -Members paul.allen
and we try to run that
We'll get an error
because the -Identity parameter
does not accept more than one group,
and we can see that, here,
as stated in the Microsoft PowerShell documentation.
It does, however, accept input from the pipeline.
We'll just use the pipeline to pass that information
onto the Add-ADGroupMember command.
A word of caution:
each PowerShell command behaves
just a little bit differently from the others.
If something doesn't work the way you think it should,
just look to the documentation.
When in doubt, look to the books!
The pipeline is represented by the pipe symbol ( | ).
It is how we can take the output of one command
from the left side of the pipe,
and use it as input of another command
on the right of the pipe.
When we use the pipeline,
it allows us to chain multiple commands together
into a super-command
that can create many more possibilities of automation.
Let's try it out and add user Paul Allen
to all of the groups that Michelle is a member of
using all that we learned so far
and chain them together with the pipeline.
Type in:
$SelectedGroups | Add-ADGroupMember
We're not going to specify the identity
because that's what we're doing on the left side of the pipe.
Then we'll type:
-Members paul.allen
Once we hit ENTER no output is given,
but we can confirm it worked in ADUC.
Awesome! That worked!
We now have completed the last part of the script.
Let's review the entire core script.
In the first part: We used Get-ADUser,
we've identified Michelle Adams,
and added the property, MemberOf, to get her group membership,
and stored that in the variable $ReferenceUser.
In the second part:
we only want to assign the groups by themselves
so we've isolated that part using
$ReferencUser.MemberOf
and assigning that output to the $SelectedGroups variable.
Then we piped those selected groups
into Add-ADGroupMember
and specified the user to add to those groups
using:
-Members paul.allen
You can verify the results of the script in ADUC
and scan the PowerShell console or any errors
that could inicate any mistakes that you might have made.
Thank you for watching, and I hoped you learned something.
As always, the script as shown
and the write-up will be uploaded to my GitHub
which is linked in the description.