Hello and welcome to Part 2.
In this video,
we'll add an interactive selection window
using Out-GridView
to our script that finds the groups of one user
and makes another user a member of those same groups.
If we compare the finished script, here,
with the one from Part 1,
we can see two changes:
First,
The SAM account names of Michelle and Paul
are assigned to variables at the very top.
Any user-defined variables
should be at the top
to make it easier to find
for anyone making changes to the script.
Our script here is fairly simple
and these SAM account names are easy to find,
but you could probably imagine the ordeal
in a script that has hundreds
or thousands of lines of code.
So it's a good habit to get into.
The second change,
is that we've added Out-GridView
to filter/select groups
before assigning to the $SelectedGroups variable.
This feature is added to the script
because there are scenarios
in which an administrator
blindly copying group membership
would be a huge problem.
Let's say that user Michelle Adams
is now a supervisor of the Sales team
at the Breakdown Lab
and has access to a restricted network folder
via the 'Sales Supervisors' group.
Our new user, Paul,
should not have access to this specific folder,
but should have access
to all other network folders for the Sales team.
We still want to leverage PowerShell
to help automate this task
but also want to have an adminstrator
filter out any groups
that may not be appropriate for our new user.
This is where Out-GridView is very useful.
What Out-GridView does
is display a PowerShell object
in an interactive table.
To show a quick example
of how the grid view displays a PowerShell object,
we'll use the Get-ADUser command
from the previous video.
We'll type:
Get-ADUser -Identity michelle.adams
Compare that to the grid view output
by piping the command into Out-GridView.
We can see that the output displays the properties
Distinguished Name, Enabled, Name, and so on.
And those are the same in the window columns.
To get a full appreciation of what Out-GridView can do,
let's try it will all AD users.
Type:
Get-ADUser -Filter * | Out-GridView
Now that we have many results with multiple properties,
we can begin to explore the features of the grid view window.
The grid view window has many features.
One of them is that you can sort the rows
by clicking on the column header.
On the first click,
you will see a small "up" arrow
indicating that the rows are sorted in acending order,
that is,
A-Z alphabetically
or small to large numerically.
On the second click,
the small arrow will change from up to down
indicating that the rows are sorted in decending order,
that is Z-A reverse alphabetically
or large to small numerically.
If you want to hide a column,
right-click on a column header
and select Select Columns...
From the Selected Columns box,
select a column name
and click on the double left arrow button
and hit OK
and it'll be removed from the window.
This field at the top
is called "Quick Filter"
and it will search all properties
of the PowerShell objects
displayed in the window
that matches the typed pattern.
If we type M-I-C-H
it would find both Michelle and Michael
because their Given Names
both begin with M-I-C-H.
To search a specific property,
click the Add criteria button
and check the box for the property to search.
In this case, select Surname.
(Surname is another name for Last Name or Family Name)
and click Add.
We'll leave the selection on contains,
but you have other filtering options.
Type in the Last Name, "Adams".
Now only Michelle Adams is shown in the results.
When you want to pass the selction
from a grid view window to the console,
you'll use the -PassThru parameter.
Now, whenever we select a user and hit OK,
the object is then output to the console.
You can output multiple users
by holding the "Control" key while clicking.
All selected users are then output to the console.
Note: hiding columns in the grid view window
does not affect the object during pass thru.
To give the window a title,
use the -Title parameter.
("O'Doyle Rules!" from Billy Madison)
Here is how we've used it in the script.
For those with a keen eye,
you'll have noticed that we've used double-quotes ( " )
instead of single quotes ( ' )
for the grid view window title text.
When using a variable in a text string,
double-quotes are used to display the value of the variable,
and single quotes are used to display the literal text.
Here's the text displaying
the target user variable with single quotes.
and the text displaying target user variable with double quotes
("Enough Talk!" from Conan the Destroyer)
This time instead of using run selection,
I'll type the name of the script file from PowerShell.
I'll then control + click the groups to add Paul to,
leaving out the Sales Supervisors group,
and hit OK.
Verify the results in ADUC.
Paul Allen now is a member of all of Michelle's groups,
except the "Sales Supervisors" group.
This concludes Part 2.
As always, the script as shown
and the write-up will be uploaded to my GitHub
which is linked in the description.
Thank you for watching, and I hoped you learned something.